Off-The-Street Club Records
University of Illinois at Chicago
Off-The-Street Club Records
1902-1975
University of Illinois at Chicago
Off-The-Street Club
9 linear ft.
The Off-The-Street Club (OTSC), Chicago's oldest boys and girls club, is a club for children and young adults located on Chicago's west side. The collection consists of annual reports, correspondence, organizational charts, newspaper clippings, newsletters, radio and television scripts, surveys, manuals, programs, published material, and photographs.
OffStreet
Administrative History
The Off-The-Street Club (OTSC), Chicago's oldest boys and girls club, is a club for children and young adults located on Chicago's west side. The Club, originally named "Juniors," was founded by John McMurray in 1898 as a safe place for unsupervised children to play. The Club was funded in its early years by the Chicago Advertising Club. Gradually, the Club began expanding its services from simply providing facilities to sponsoring programs including health care programs, and a summer camp in Wheaton, Illinois. In 1955, the Club moved from its Jackson Boulevard premises to the West Garfield Park community.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of annual reports, correspondence, organizational charts, newspaper clippings, newsletters, radio and television scripts, surveys, manuals, programs, published material, and photographs. The materials pertain to the OTSC programs and activities, fundraising appeals, conventions, August Mathieu, and Work Projects Administration activities.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Mathieu, August--Sources.; Off-the-Street Club (Chicago, Ill.)--Archives.; United States. Work Projects Administration (Ill.)--Sources.; Garfield Park (Chicago, Ill.)--Sources.
Hull-House and Settlement House History
Detailed Description/Box and Folder Listing
- Series I
  - Annual reports, 1902-1931 (Box 0, Folder 1)
  - Annual reports, 1932 (Box 0, Folder 2)
  - Annual reports, 1937-1940 (Box 0, Folder 3)
  - Annual reports, 1941 (Box 0, Folder 4)
  - Annual reports, 1943-1964 (Box 0, Folder 5)
  - Appeal to Wieboldt Foundation, 1937-1940 (Box 0, Folder 6)
  - Boys Club conventions, 1937-1962 (Box 0, Folder 7)
  - Character guild, 1920-1932 (Box 0, Folder 8)
  - Charles Stoddard Jubilee Dinner, 1925 (Box 0, Folder 9)
  - Cheating the Streets, 1939 (Box 0, Folder 10)
  - Club members' activities, 1945-1961 (Box 0, Folder 11)
  - Community Fund allocations, 1938 (Box 0, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence - letters from soldiers, 1942-1951 (Box 0, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1964 (Box 0, Folder 14)
  - Early history of club, 1916-1929 (Box 0, Folder 15)
  - Financial aid - Atlas Club benefits, 1909-1926 (Box 0, Folder 16)
  - Financial aid - baseball games, 1917-1925 (Box 0, Folder 17)
  - Financial aid - Grand Beach County Fair, 1918-1923 (Box 0, Folder 18)
  - Financial aid - Junior Women's Advertising Club Fashion Show, 1957-1962 (Box 0, Folder 19)
  - Financial aid - benefits, 1920-1962 (Box 0, Folder 20)
  - Founders of club, 1903-1961 (Box 0, Folder 21)
  - Garfield Community Organizations, 1941-1966 (Box 0, Folder 22)
  - General information and organizational charts, 1945-1957 (Box 0, Folder 23)
  - Instructors' reports, 1939-1940 (Box 0, Folder 24)
  - Jackson branch, 1938-1957 (Box 0, Folder 25)
  - Karlov Club, 1955 (Box 0, Folder 26)
  - Letterhead, 1928-1969 (Box 0, Folder 27)
  - Mathieu - misc, 1930-1966 (Box 0, Folder 28)
  - Membership in club, 1953-1954 (Box 0, Folder 29)
  - Midwest Community Council -- Administration, 1950-1952 (Box 0, Folder 30)
  - Midwest Community Council - Better homes and yards, 1950-1952 (Box 0, Folder 31)
  - Midwest Community Council - Camping, 1951 (Box 0, Folder 32)
  - Midwest Community Council - Clean-up campaign, 1950-1957 (Box 0, Folder 33)
  - Midwest Community Council - council agencies, undated (Box 0, Folder 34)
  - Midwest Community Council - housing, 1951 (Box 0, Folder 35)
  - Midwest Community Council - recreation - volunteer training, 1949-1950 (Box 0, Folder 36)
  - Midwest Community Council - schools, undated (Box 0, Folder 37)
  - Midwest Community Council, 1948-1962 (Box 0, Folder 38)
  - Morris B. Sachs Radio Program, 1941-1942 (Box 0, Folder 39)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1940-1945 (Box 0, Folder 40)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1940-1945 (Box 0, Folder 41)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1946-1949 (Box 0, Folder 42)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1950 (Box 0, Folder 43)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1951-1953 (Box 0, Folder 44)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1954-1955 (Box 0, Folder 45)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1956 (Box 0, Folder 46)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1957 (Box 0, Folder 47)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1958 (Box 0, Folder 48)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1959 (Box 0, Folder 49)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1960 (Box 0, Folder 50)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1961 (Box 0, Folder 51)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1962-1967 (Box 0, Folder 52)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 0, Folder 53)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1940-1965 (Box 0, Folder 54)
  - Notebook - friends, 1939-1965 (Box 0, Folder 55)
  - Notebook - friends, 1913-1968 (Box 0, Folder 56)
  - Notebook - friends, 1957-1968 (Box 0, Folder 57)
  - Notebook - friends, 1965-1968 (Box 0, Folder 58)
  - Notebook - Mathieu retirement, 1966-1968 (Box 0, Folder 59)
  - Notebook - Off the Street Club, 1946-1952 (Box 0, Folder 60)
  - Notebook - published material -- lectures #1, 1928-1965 (Box 0, Folder 61)
  - Notebook - published material - lectures, 1944-1964 (Box 0, Folder 62)
  - Off the Street Club manual, 1940 (Box 0, Folder 63)
  - Photographs - Christmas, 1950-1965 (Box 0, Folder 64)
  - Photographs - Day Camp, undated (Box 0, Folder 65)
  - Photographs - early activities, 1907-1922 (Box 0, Folder 66)
  - Photographs - from notebooks, 1913-1968 (Box 0, Folder 67)
  - Photographs - misc., 1936-1960 (Box 0, Folder 68)
  - Proceedings of Boys Clubs Association of Chicago Conference, 1930 (Box 0, Folder 69)
  - Program - activities outside of club, 1961 (Box 0, Folder 70)
  - Program - Christmas activities, 1941-1965 (Box 0, Folder 71)
  - Program - Day camp, 1939-1941 (Box 0, Folder 72)
  - Program - early programs, 1904-1920 (Box 0, Folder 73)
  - Program - report and notebook, 1931-1942 (Box 0, Folder 74)
  - Program - schedules, 1933-1962 (Box 0, Folder 75)
  - Program - special events, 1932-1961 (Box 0, Folder 76)
  - Program - sports, 1937-1960 (Box 0, Folder 77)
  - Program - summer activities, 1936-1944 (Box 0, Folder 78)
  - Program - summer camp, 1945-1964 (Box 0, Folder 79)
  - Program - summer programs report, 1941 (Box 0, Folder 80)
  - Program - misc., 1929-1959 (Box 0, Folder 81)
  - Publications - administrative bulletin, 1941-1942 (Box 0, Folder 82)
  - Publications - The Bulletin, 1916-1922 (Box 0, Folder 83)
  - Publications - Newsletter, 1957-1966 (Box 0, Folder 84)
  - Publications - Our Compass, 1931-1938 (Box 0, Folder 85)
  - Publications - Sport Comments, 1941-1943 (Box 0, Folder 86)
  - Publications - Staff Bulletin, 1939-1941 (Box 0, Folder 87)
  - Publications - West Side Inter-Club Council Newsletter, 1940-1941 (Box 0, Folder 88)
  - Publications - You Should Know, 1946-1953 (Box 0, Folder 89)
  - Publicity, magazine articles, 1941-1966 (Box 0, Folder 90)
  - Radio Programs, 1932-1946 (Box 0, Folder 91)
  - Recreation conferences, 1941-1966 (Box 0, Folder 92)
  - Rehabilitation of parolees, 1941 (Box 0, Folder 93)
  - Sacramento club, 1958 (Box 0, Folder 94)
  - Scouting, 1931-1958 (Box 0, Folder 95)
  - Statement of objectives and early club history, 1929 (Box 0, Folder 96)
  - Survey of Off the Street Club by Northwestern, 1929 (Box 0, Folder 97)
  - True Story Series, 1941-1961 (Box 0, Folder 98)
  - TV Program, 1949 (Box 0, Folder 99)
  - Van Buren Club, 1914-1940 (Box 0, Folder 100)
  - Works Projects Administration activities, 1938-1941 (Box 0, Folder 101)
- Supplement I
  - Advertising Club News and Christmas benefit programs, 1905-1975 (Box 0, Folder 1)
  - Articles about gangs, 1972-973 (Box 0, Folder 2)
  - Articles of incorporation, 1916 (Box 0, Folder 3)
  - Auditors examination of records, 1916-1936 (Box 0, Folder 4)
  - Boys clubs, 1933-1956 (Box 0, Folder 5)
  - Boys clubs association of Chicago Conference, 1940 (Box 0, Folder 6)
  - Cheating the Streets, 1939 (Box 0, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence about closing the Van Burn branch, 1942 (Box 0, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1955 (Box 0, Folder 9)
  - Jackie's column from the Midwest News, 1944-1945 (Box 0, Folder 10)
  - Letterhead, 1016-1953 (Box 0, Folder 11)
  - Mathieu - biographical information, 1957-1976 (Box 0, Folder 12)
  - Mathieu - misc. activities, 1944-1971 (Box 0, Folder 13)
  - Mathieu - personal, 1948-1975 (Box 0, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous, 1918-1957 (Box 0, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1937-1964 (Box 0, Folder 16)
  - Notebook - camp, 1956-1958 (Box 0, Folder 17)
  - Notebook - camp, 1945-1959 (Box 0, Folder 18)
  - Notebook - club activities, 1954-1956 (Box 0, Folder 19)
  - Notebook - history, 1955-1956 (Box 0, Folder 20)
  - Notebook - history, 1938-1955 (Box 0, Folder 21)
  - Notebook - Midwest Community Council, 1951-1975 (Box 0, Folder 22)
  - Photographs - Mathieu, 1960 -1964 (Box 0, Folder 23)
  - Photographs - misc., 1920 -1956 (Box 0, Folder 24)
  - Photographs - camp, 1956-1958 (Box 0, Folder 25)
  - Photographs - camp, 1035-1950 (Box 0, Folder 26)
  - Photographs - Club activities, 19422-1952 (Box 0, Folder 27)
  - Photographs - Club activities, 1949-1960 (Box 0, Folder 28)
  - Photographs - history, 1955-1956 (Box 0, Folder 29)
  - Photographs - history, 1934-958 (Box 0, Folder 30)
  - Photographs - summer 1964, 1960-1964 (Box 0, Folder 31)
  - Program, 1913-1964 (Box 0, Folder 32)
  - Program, home camp, 1938-1940 (Box 0, Folder 33)
  - Publications - administrative bulletins, 1941-1942 (Box 0, Folder 34)
  - Publications - "Of Mutual Interest", 1940-1943 (Box 0, Folder 35)
  - Publications - Staff bulletins, 1939-1941 (Box 0, Folder 36)
  - Report to Community Fund and Welfare Council, 1941 (Box 0, Folder 37)
  - Seventy-fifth anniversary letters, 1975 (Box 0, Folder 38)
  - Youth on Parade program, 1945-1948 (Box 0, Folder 39)
  - Oversized: Photographs - Mark Twain Adventure camp, undated (Box 0, Folder 40)
- Supplement 2
  - Correspondence: Mathieu Family - 1768-21 June, 1952 (Box 0, Folder 1)
  - Documents: Gove Family - 29 Apr., 1838-22 Oct., 1919 (Box 0, Folder 2)
  - Documents: A.Mathieu - Personal, 1901-1979 (Box 0, Folder 3)
  - Photographs: A.Mathieu, 1932-1966 (Box 0, Folder 4)
  - Automatic Canteen Company - September, 1932 (Box 0, Folder 5)
  - Publications: Century of Progress Exhibit, 1933 (Box 0, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: A. Mathieu - Business - 11 Oct., 1933-21 Jun., 1982 (Box 0, Folder 7)
  - Program: Training Course - 1 Oct., 1935-16 Nov., 1936 (Box 0, Folder 8)
  - Speeches: A. Mathieu - 23 March, 1936-20 Oct., 1966 (Box 0, Folder 9)
  - Program: BCC Annual Conference - 23 March, 1936-March, 1939 (Box 0, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper Clippings: OTSC - 5 Sep., 1937-7 June, 1989 (Box 0, Folder 11)
  - Program: BCA Annual Convention - 15-18 May, 1939-13 May, 1968 (Box 0, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: A. Mathieu - Personal - 8 June, 1939-12 Feb., 1980 (Box 0, Folder 13)
  - Publications: Staff Bulletins - 1 Sept., 1939-1 Apr., 1941 (Box 0, Folder 14)
  - Photographs: Club Activities - 1940-1982 (Box 0, Folder 15)
  - Publications: OTSC Events - 21 Dec., 1940-3 March, 1947 (Box 0, Folder 16)
  - Photographs: Day Camp- 1941-1981 (Box 0, Folder 17)
  - Morris B. Sachs Amateur Hour - May, 1941 (Box 0, Folder 18)
  - Program: Victory Volunteers - 27 May, 1942 (Box 0, Folder 19)
  - Program: Pure Milk Farm Visit - 7 June, 1941 (Box 0, Folder 20)
  - Report to Community Fund and Welfare Council - 14 Oct., 1941 (Box 0, Folder 21)
  - Program: Youth on Parade - 12 June, 1945-25 June, 1948 (Box 0, Folder 22)
  - Publications: "You Should Know" - 5 July, 1945-27 May, 1947 (Box 0, Folder 23)
  - Publications: CFDC News - Dec. 1945-Feb. 1953 (Box 0, Folder 24)
  - Program: Annual Christmas Party - 22 Dec., 1945-8 Dec., 1978 (Box 0, Folder 25)
  - OTSC Christmas Letter - December, 1946 (Box 0, Folder 26)
  - Newspaper Clippings: Day Camp - 21 Aug., 1955-22 Aug., 1979 (Box 0, Folder 27)
  - Midwest Community Council: Annual Dinner Meeting - 22 May, 1961 (Box 0, Folder 28)
  - Publications: Attendance - March, 1963 (Box 0, Folder 29)
  - Garfield Family Council: Invitation - 7 March, 1963 (Box 0, Folder 30)
  - Publications: Survey Report - June, 1963 (Box 0, Folder 31)
  - Publications: Day Camp Christmas News - 14 Dec., 1963 (Box 0, Folder 32)
  - Publications: Annual Meeting - 22 June, 1965 (Box 0, Folder 33)
  - Program: Acceptance of Club Program by Community Leaders - 17 Jan., 1966 (Box 0, Folder 34)
  - 75th Anniversary Letters - 25 Apr., 1975-Dec., 1975 (Box 0, Folder 35)
  - Publications: OTSC Pamphlets - 1979-1993 (Box 0, Folder 36)
  - Publications: Pro Files - Spring, 1979 (Box 0, Folder 37)
  - Program: Annual Christmas Party - 20 Dec., 1979-15 Dec., 1989 (Box 0, Folder 38)
  - Magazine: Connections - Summer, 1981 (Box 0, Folder 39)
  - OTSC 82nd Annual Meeting - 16 Jun., 1982 (Box 0, Folder 40)
  - Newspaper Clippings: Green Chicago - 18 Sept., 1994 (Box 0, Folder 41)
  - Midwest Community Council: Invitation, undated (Box 0, Folder 42)
  - Photographs: A.Mathieu, Photographer, undated (Box 0, Folder 43)
  - Program: An Evening of the Nations, undated (Box 0, Folder 44)
  - Program: Roller Skating Program, undated (Box 0, Folder 45)
  - Publications: Community Churches of America, undated (Box 0, Folder 46)
  - Publications: Delphian, vol. 3, undated (Box 0, Folder 47)
  - Publications: Junior Leader Club Members, undated (Box 0, Folder 48)